President Crave, we do have Dr. Renie
and Councilman White online.
Good afternoon and welcome to the August
21st, 2026
work session. Uh today's work session
will address the urban farm unified
development code updates.
This is a educational uh meeting. We
will not be taking public testimony. As
you may recall, this is uh this came up
during the annexation of county pocket,
our 10th uh pocket that we were
annexing, and it was postponed on March
9th to give uh the development office an
opportunity to review all of our unified
development codes.
Um, two items will be heard at the
public services committee on November
2nd. That was our postponement to that
time. And then their recommendation will
for third reading will come to the full
council on November 9th. With that, uh,
Director Bloom, you've had some time to
review and study and make some
recommendations. So, why don't you take
it away? And he has agreed that we can
ask questions as we go through this.
>> Okay. Thank you. and chair, members of
the committee, Charles Bloom, planning
and development director. Um, first of
all, I can't take all the credit for
this. The law of this was put together
with a collaboration of staff. Um, it's
been put together over the course of
several um months actually. Um, when
this initially was postponed earlier
this year, um, we we had a lot of extra
time at that time and then a lot of
other things kind of fell upon us. So it
was very uh very timeconuming to put
this together um to deal with the other
things that have been going on. So seems
like we we never get a break anymore
with the development processes here.
Something is always popping up. But we
do feel we we put together a pretty good
um solution that provides some certainty
for folks that are being annexed that
have agricultural uses and also um
provides some more certainty that needs
to be done for the everyday citizen in
the community because um our farm and
ranch related ordinances have not been
updated in a very long time and they
don't necessarily uh fall in line with
state statute.
Um so what what I'm going to do today is
I'm going to um go through a
presentation. It's about a total of 14
slides from this point on. Um the first
section is going to talk a little bit
about definitions um that we're adding
and modifying in the development code.
Um and then we'll move on to um some
items regarding um home occupations,
site plan requirements, development
standards, and then we'll move on to
some other targeted amendments that will
occur in the municipal code. In the end,
what we do expect will be a total of uh
I believe it's four different ordinances
that will run in tandem, which we would
introduce to the governing body at the
second meeting in September. So they
would be complete by the final meeting
in October which gives uh you another
meeting if you wish to postpone um to
align it perfectly with the third and
final reading of the uh annexation
consideration of the county pockets.
So first of all, we've modified the
general agriculture definition uh just a
little bit. Primarily on this uh we um
added um that it includes smallcale
intermittent harvesting and processing
of livestock raised primarily on
premise. Um this this is something that
was not clarified in the general
agriculture definition before. So with
with that um we've uh strengthened the
general agriculture definition so it is
more understandable more recognizable as
to what that use is. So this would allow
um a variety of different agricultural
uses, you know, ranching, farming. This
could have um harvesting of chickens
that might be on a person's property.
This could be uh maybe they have one or
two or three cows. Um that that that
could be done. This specifically
includes concentrated feeding
operations, which are ones that you're
more familiar with with the larger um
type of facilities that you might notice
south of here along US85. There's some
concentrated feeding operations and such
um outside of Gley, Colorado.
Um,
>> chairman C. Grave through you. So, would
this proposed change be in all zones or
would this only be in things that are
agg zoned?
>> Um, at the end I'll have a the use
table. My computer is frozen so I can't
get to my memo so I have to double check
where that is.
>> And a follow-up question. And so we
would be basically allowing butchering
even of larger animals like cows and
goats and things like that.
>> Correct. The general agriculture um this
would be primarily permitted in the um
the P the public zone, the business park
zone, conditional use in the light
industrial and the HI zone um and also
in the A and the AR zone. So that would
be in zone districts. uh that would be
customary where you would see general
agricultural um activities. Um I'll get
on to a little bit further. I'll get in
to where it would allow for home
occupations and those uses to be as home
occupations.
>> Mr. Mr. President.
>> Yeah. Yes. Uh thank you uh Mr. President
through you. Um first of all, Mr. Bloom,
I want to thank you very much for all
your work on this and and your staff's
work. Um, obviously reflects a lot of
thought and it looks like a lot of uh
kind of needed updating of um of kind of
long outdated rules and ordinances. Um,
one thing that just occurred to me and
and you can answer it at at your
convenience um, this afternoon is does
any of this affect um, people either
processing their own hunted wildlife or
the people who are in the business of
processing wildlife during hunting
season
and chair through you to council member
Wolf. No, this would not um affect them
negatively in any way. Um it would in
fact provide more clarification that
this is something that could be done. Um
one of the provisions in the home
occupation portion of code um it does
talk about um these these type of
operations that would be allowed. Thank
you very much.
I'm going to pass these out to you all
real quick.
>> No, the short answer is no. It would not
negatively affect them.
>> Dr. Evans,
>> thank you, Mr. Chair. Um, can you
explain
probably to more than just me what a
concentrating feeding operation entails,
please?
>> Uh, yes. I can actually go to our
definition. This is a proposed new
definition. A concentrated feeding
operation of slaughterhouse is an
agricultural use where livestock are
confined, fed, and maintained for 45
consecutive days or more in a 12-month
period or livestock stock are harvested
as a principal use. The use does not
include customary non-commercial animal
harvest as an accessory use to a primary
residential or standard agricultural
operation.
So this is describing your large scale
um facility where the primary purpose is
animal slaughter and feeding operations.
And this actually
provides that exclusion
that council member Wolf and um council
member Moody had just inquired about
regarding um butchering of animals
during hunting season at a private
residence or as a small business related
to a private residence.
So for clarification, if I have a cow
that I use for milk to sell, that is
does not fall into the concentrating
concentrated feeding operations.
>> Chair through to Dr. Emmens. That is
correct.
>> Um and then one more followup. So if I
have five cows
and I'm going to harvest one of them to
sell the meat, is that a concentrated
feeding operation?
director and chair through you. That is
not a concentrated feeding operation. It
because the principal use of the land
still is in your scenario the
residential use.
>> Okay. Thank you.
>> All right.
Chair, members of council, this is a
second new definition that we are
adding. This is the definition that
aligns with the state statute uh
1149102.
This is in regarding regard this is
regarding gardens and homemade foods. Um
basically any property producing food
for sale whose usage meets the
definition of a producer according to
state statute and we reference the state
statute. We don't spell it out because
state statutes change. So we just want
to keep the the bookmark there so we can
align with state statute as it changes.
Um these are um this is this is a use
this includes um gardens and um homemade
foods which include livestock and this
can be in
the zone district um where the principal
use is allowed. For example, if you have
a residence where you have your five
cattle, your chickens, your hens, maybe
you have a large uh garden um and you
wish to sell food. Um you can sell that
to um anyone for for sale at a at a
community sale center. you could um sell
it to a retailer, you know, to sell in
in those cases. You could do that. under
state statute.
Um the definition of a of a person who
is
who is um producing
homemade foods and homemade items is one
that is not uh having gross sales of
over $250,000
annually. So this essentially limits it
to
smaller
um sales, smallcale operations, nothing
large.
And when we get to the use table
summary, you'll see that gardens and
homemade foods are broadly allowed in
our U proposed changes.
Um the second additional definition that
we've added is one regarding
agricultural product sales and farmers
markets.
Um this is a a new definition that is
added. Um this is one that provides
additional clarification
as to what this use is. This essentially
is um defining a farmers market um and
what that is comprised of. Um as
expected, it kind of mirrors what we see
in our community today, which is a
collection of um different trucks,
trailers, or outbuildings that can be
used for the retail sale of agricultural
products and operate without any
permanent on-site facilities that would
be associated with an agricultural use.
This includes uh road roadside stands,
um food stands and uh sales from trucks
and trailers
um and also barn sales are examples of
such um uses.
Now these are categorized that they are
not um super intense
um which means that the frequency of uh
these types of um uses uh should not
require additional parking um or
warehouses or storage facilities on the
site. Um and they uh characterize it as
having less than 2,000 uh square ft of
gross leasable area. So essentially what
this is is these are smaller facilities
um that are not permanent um they are
able to be easily removed and uh they
don't uh trigger uh massive site
improvements.
>> Mr. Chair,
>> Dr.
>> Thank you. Um, so when you say not
permanent, how how are we I mean I I've
got the 2,000 square feet and the
parking, but what makes it not
permanent? Does that mean it's not
attached to a sewer system or do we have
guidelines around that?
>> Director chair through to the committee
um of the whole the committee. Typically
this
these type of uses none of these would
be buildings that would be publicly
occupied. So they would not have uh the
need for those con um connections to the
sewer um or electricity and such. Um
once you start having the public
occupation, they fall into a different
element of the building code which that
would require um certain inspections,
certain permits and certain building
standards. Um so in this specific case,
these would be more of what you would
see as traditional um product sales
where they would be conducted either
outside or through pass through windows
of those types.
>> Dr.
>> Thank you, Mr. chair. So for
clarification, if you have a farm stand
that is selling something they're making
and they have to have a commercial sink
or commercial
connections, they would they would be
considered permanent,
>> right?
>> Chair through you. That is correct.
>> Okay. Chairman C. Thank you,
>> Dr. Aldridge. Germany great through you.
I guess I would like to challenge that a
little bit because there are portable
sinks that are commonly used in culinary
arts um for temporary setups. Um I'm
thinking of a farm stand we have in our
community right now that has a temporary
sink setup that um and they sell them
all the time for catering events um that
are basically a canister with a spigot
and water and soap dispenser. kind of
looks like something you'd get for a
camping situation. Um, so that
handashing can be done, but it they're
not drained into like a sewer system or
something. So, what you're saying is is
that if they have if they're in a
situation where they have to have a
handwashing situation, that would then
be considered permanent. I I would
challenge that,
>> director chair, through you through you
for clarification. Um, I I believe I
miss mis uh heard the question. I was
understanding that if it needed a
permanent sewer connection,
>> that's what I was asking.
>> If it's a permanent sewer connection,
yes, that would be one thing. If it's a
if it's acceptable through county health
for like a handwashing station, the
different compartmentalized sink, and
that could all be taken care of with
with their their water waste container
and water supply that would indeed be
temporary, not considered permanent.
>> Thank you. So in both scenarios they're
correct. Dr.
>> Thank you sir. I have one more question.
Um with the permanent have you
considered that permanent any kind of a
time frame? So permanent may be six
months of the year, nine months of the
year
through you. We do have we have um
thought about what permit is and that
falls onto our
our temporary use provisions which
essentially if something is greater than
6 months um then it is considered a
permanent use.
>> Sorry. So for clarification, if it's
under six months, so say it's just
summer time, then it would not be
permanent, even though it may be I want
to say hardwired, that's not the right
word, but you know, plumbed in or
something like that. If it was only if
it was operated less than six months, it
would not be permanent.
>> Chair through you. That is correct.
>> Okay. Thank you. I had one follow-up
question,
>> Dr. Aldrich.
>> Uh Mr. Seager, through you. Um, I had
one follow-up question and that is we
have a situation right now in our
community where um, at the roundabout
there is the portable shed that's on I
don't I don't know do they call it on
skids or something so that it can be
moved. Um, but you said that this was uh
for agriculture product sales and
farmers markets that were buildings
basically not for the public. So if the
you said a drive a pass through window
or a situation where it was open air
basically. So if you have a situation
like this temporary
a shed I guess that is now a a small
building and people go into it to shop
like for t-shirts and things I think is
primarily what they've been selling. But
if they were to sell salsas or food
items or things like that because they
have a neighboring stand that does those
things, would that then be considered
not to fall under this category because
um the public is allowed into that
building to shop
>> director and chair through Dr. Aldrich.
I'm very familiar with that site up
there. um
that one would the way it was described
where public would be going into the
structure um that that would not fall
into this category. Um with the public
occupying a structure, it would
essentially be considered a a principal
building, it would be subject to
building code review. Um it would have
to meet building code standards um to
have public occupancy.
>> Great. Thank you.
Thank you.
All right. Something else that we've
added is a definition of agurism. And
agurism is a more modern term um that is
in a lot of different development
regulations. And this is very broad and
encompasses a lot of uh different types
of uses. Um primarily this is the um
ability for someone to operate temporary
uses on a site which could be you know
tours of working farms, ranches, could
have educational um components to it. Um
it could have corn mazes, pumpkin
patches, petting zoos, similar uses like
that. Um so this is a catchall to allow
um different types of uses that could
occur um on a site.
Um we typically don't see um too many
agurism uses in this area but if we were
we would be prepared and have the
ability to um to classify it. Excage.
>> Um, chairman Crave through you. Uh, so
under I don't see included under this
definition. I mean, we have some
events in our community that for our uh
large outdoor dinners that are prepared
and sold. Um, I'm thinking primarily
right now the one a couple that I've
attended through visit Cheyenne and have
not been within the city limits. But if
we were to have a venue that wanted to
do some sort of a slow roast dinner
which is similar to what visit Cheyenne
has done that is not is that allowable
under this agurism because it doesn't
seem like that activity or use is
similar to any of these that are listed
>> chair through you um to Dr. Aldridge.
What I'm envisioning there is something
like a large uh catered meal with like a
pig growth, something along those lines,
>> right?
>> Um that would essentially be a temporary
use where it' be like an assembly
gathering where people would be
assembling and they would be licensed by
environmental health with their
temporary permits that would be needed.
So it would be something different than
agurism.
>> Okay. Thank you.
Um again there's the definition of the
concentrated feeding operations uh which
uh we clarify that um that does not
include customarily non-commercial
animal harvest which is an accessory
used to a primary residential or
standard agricultural operation
something we wanted to work in here
which was a discussion point.
>> Yes
>> Mr. Chair, sorry. Uh, this Councilman
White, I did have a question on that
definition, Mr. Bloom. Um, where does
the 45 consecutive days come from? Was
there some type of specific data that
supported that time frame? I'm just kind
of wondering how you came up with 45
consecutive days.
>> Chair through you to council member
White. Um, this is just what we we found
through our different searches of
different codes. It seemed to be a
standard number um that seemed to work
uh very well. Um so that was one that we
had we had um utilized.
>> Thank you.
>> Get some more. I can get some more
information from staff as to if there
was more um justification for that
number and get back to you. Question.
>> Councilman.
>> Thank you, Mr. President. Through you.
Um just question. You say look through
various codes. Are they ones within
Wyoming, Pine Bluffs, Torington, Casper,
Cody, Sheridan?
>> Tear three to Council Member Moody. Um
there were a variety of different codes
we had looked at. I know we had looked
at um Boulder County, we had looked at
uh city of Gley, we had looked at um
some in Nebraska and and other areas.
Um, but I don't know the exact um, which
pieces came from what areas, but it was
a conglomeration of a bunch of different
codes and what we felt worked best for
the community.
Thank you.
One item that was um, noted during the
um, annexation discussions was site plan
exemptions. So we utilize this as a time
to up to update our site plan
exemptions. Presently we have a variety
of scenarios where site plans are not
required. Um we've clarified um a couple
of other cases. Um item number C is the
one that's directly related to
agriculture. Um, this is that if um a
use is not expected to have a
significant customer impact um like a
garden nursery with no on-site sales, if
someone's doing gardens or homemade
foods on site or uh general agriculture,
those will be exempt from having to
provide a site plan. So if someone were
to establish a a new agricultural use or
expand a new use, they would not need to
go through the site plan process to
identify exactly where everything goes
on their site. Um this does not exempt
them from any required um building
permits that they may need um for the
use of their property. Um, also with
this, we um did add in some additional
exemptions that um should have probably
been added in before. One for
cemeteries. We don't necessarily need a
se site plan for a cemetery. Those
already go through a subdivision process
that's man mandated by the state so we
know where everything is. um military
missionoriented facilities, which should
provide some clarification between um us
and the federal government and the
National Guard regarding um future
development on their sites. Um and also
um limited business operations occurring
um um in a residential unit. Um so we've
modified um those to clarify that site
plans um aren't required.
So, um, specifically, um, item number B
provides clarification for a lot of our
family child care homes and family child
care centers, um, and home occupations
where it's not clear in our development
regulations that a site plan is not
required even though they are typically
occurring inside an established
residential dwelling unit with the
exception of maybe, you know, outdoor
play that might occur in a designated
side or backyard.
We we have a question online. Jennifer
>> Councilman White, you can go ahead.
>> Thank you. Uh President Crave through
you to Director Bloom. Under section C,
uh Charles,
what does no significant customer
impacts mean? And who it seems kind of
subjective to me. And who determines
that?
chair through you to council member
White. Um yes, that is it is not
necessarily clear. Um and it is
subjective, but a lot of the development
code is subjective in the way where even
when you're looking at your decision
making on special use permits, the
planning commission and the board of or
the board of adjustments looking at
their decision making on harmony with
the neighborhood, it's up to an
interpretation as to whether or not
something meets the criteria. Um, in
this specific case, it's hard to um
identify an actual trip count. Um, so
what we're looking at is is roughly is
it something that is noticeable by the
public or generating uh traffic that
people would notice. Um, so it is it is
subjective. Um, and it's going to be
based on the termination of the the
director at that time. In
in our typical home occupation
scenarios, um generally
um when you have a home occupation,
you're looking at something that is
commensurate with the neighborhood. Um
typically a single family home generates
about 10 trips per day. Um a multifamily
dwelling unit generates about eight
trips a day. It's pretty much stayed
around that level for quite some time.
um if there's about a 10 to 20% uh jump
because of this change of use um I
wouldn't expect that to be
um having a significant impact.
>> Thank you, Dr. Aldrich.
>> Chairman Crave through you. Uh so I have
a couple of questions with your response
to Councilman White.
If this bypasses the site plan process
because it's with this is under site
plan exemption
um then that significant customer impact
you mentioned the um board of exception
or board of adjustments that would never
when would it ever come to the board of
adjustments if this bypasses the site
plan
>> chair through Dr. alters. This would not
go to the board of adjustment at all. I
just use the board of adjustment as an
example of of a board that has um
some review criteria that aren't clearly
lined out as to
a quantity or a specific scenario where
they're based on an opinion or um a
conclusion that they make based on how
something relates to a neighborhood. So
would this would be solely at your
discretion
>> chair. That is correct.
>> Yeah, I find that really problematic. Um
the other question I had was are we not
having family child care homes or family
child care centers or um go through the
site plan process because they're
expected to go through the state
licensing process which then utilizes
site plans.
>> Tier three to Dr. Aldridge. That is
correct. And it's a duplication because
they're already regulated by the state
through their process.
>> Thank you.
>> And the and the count city county
health.
>> Thank you.
>> All right. This is the changes to the
use table. What we've done is we've
pulled out just the uh uses that were
noted that are agriculture related. um
general agriculture. Um we've
highlighted that a little bit. What we
see on this first slide is the AG
through CBD. So this is your
agricultural uses, your residential, and
the beginning of your your commercial
uses. The latter slide will have the
industrial uses and and other um
industrial zone districts and other zone
districts that are more intense. Um
gardens and homemade foods. That's the
one that's um set to um clarify that
anyone can essentially have a garden.
You know, you can harvest your um animal
that you've um brought back from a
hunting trip. That is permissible in
every um zone.
Um we have uh changes to the
agricultural product um sales and
farmers market where we're clarifying
that that new use um that is able to be
done in the AG and the AR zone
districts. Those are the agriculture and
agricultural residential zone districts
and then we've also added them to the
neighborhood business community business
and the CBD zone district.
>> Mr. Chair,
>> Dr. Emmens.
through you um Charles before you go any
further and again I apologize if this is
a really dumb question but what does P
mean and what does C
>> that's all right um P means permitted
use that means it is one that all they
would do is either apply for a site plan
if necessary or um if no site plan is
required they would also um just need to
apply for any applicable building
permits that means it's all an
administrative process The C means
conditional use. That means it would
have to go to the board of adjustment
for approval.
Yep, that's right. Fair question. Um
sometimes they get trapped in the lingo
and and forget to to mention to
everybody.
Um so then what we've um done is we've
uh changed the we've added the
concentrated feeding operations and
slaughter houses and these uses um
they're typically very political. They
do utilize a lot of water and there's a
heavy water usage with these. Um so
these we've assigned um to the a zone
and we've added them as an S which is a
special use which means that these would
go directly to the governing body for
consideration.
So this would be a discussion um for you
all um as to whether or not you would
want to have this type of facility in
the community.
So that would be in the a zone district.
Um and then the other the other half of
the use table um those concentrated
feeding operations again they'd be
allowed in the light industrial, heavy
industrial and the business park zone
district. However, they'd be subject to
a special use approval by the by the
governing body.
Um again you can see that um in the use
table the
gardens and homemade foods they're
permissible across the board. Um they'll
be permitted um uses where one can do
that without um any public approval. Um
and in the case of like single family
homes no no permits um you required for
that.
Any questions on the the use table? And
again, this is these are all
recommendations. We're going to take
what we've heard from you all because
we're not planning on taking this to the
planning commission for about 3 weeks
and we're going to fine-tune this based
on the comments we received from the
public and based on comments we received
from you all the next week so we can
finalize the ordinance.
Um so for home occupations we've
clarified
um as a exemption um to requiring a home
occupation permit which basically we
have a home occupation permit in our
development code right now which
basically is just a registration saying
hey this is what I'm doing. It's
complied with sometimes but not all the
time. Um, but we're clarifying that you
don't need to um declare that you have a
home occupation for um your home garden
or your small um urban farm for lack of
a better term that you may have on your
your back 40.
>> Question.
>> Dr. Enrich.
>> Um I would Councilman Seager through
you. I would suggest that we add the
word permit after home occupation in
that second line.
um because it doesn't say that
currently. So where it says home uh from
requiring a home occupation if the
garden and homemade foods. So we need to
make sure we add the word from requiring
a home occupation permit
um inserting that there. And uh as a
followup, so when you said
you you used the example of an urban
farm,
you said if they uh were a small urban
farm, which by our definition is the
less than $250,000 per year in revenue.
Correct.
23 and Dr. Aldrich. That is correct.
>> Thank you.
So, we've also added um parking area
modifications. Um these are ones that um
will actually benefit more than just the
agricultural uses.
So, these are exemptions and these are
just summarized um here.
Um with the paving exemptions,
uh this would um exempt agricultural
uses like working farms, farm stands,
and agricultural um lands and agurism
from having to pave their parking areas.
For example, in the um using the example
of the Wfresh farms, which is ones one
we're all pretty familiar with, um they
would not need to pave their parking
area as part of um a site plan because
they're primarily agricultural use. So,
that would not be required. Um we've
also clarified that single family
residential
um doesn't need to have paved parking
areas. Uh right now um if you interpret
the code literally um any area that is
used for maneuvering for vehicles
technically is required to be paved. Um
so even if you have a large lot with a
long driveway, you would be required to
have a paved driveway. Um, this would
inherently allow for people to put in
gravel driveways um and such. Um, but
that is already occurring in some areas
where you have side drives, rear drives,
driveways off of alleys where there are
gravel right now. This would recognize a
lot of the development patterns that
have already occurred and it could um
introduce um the ability for um you know
other um surface treatments for
driveways and in certain areas.
Um we have another um addition for
paving exemption. Uh this is uh for
parking areas that are used fewer than
55 times per year. Um so this would be
for civic uses, event venues, um
assembly venues, churches, parks, trail
heads and such. Um this would be um
primarily for uses where you may only
need um parking at that capacity for a
limited period of time. Um this most
commonly associated with uh churches and
parks. Um, so this is a an exemption
that we're we're putting into place
because as we all know, the more we
pave, the more storm water drainage we
we have to um deal with and mitigate in
the future.
And then we put a provision in here um
that
if that is a regard to regional storm
water management um that um essentially
allows for an exemption
um if and it should say city engineer. I
thought I'd change that and I'm a little
worried how the rest of this
presentation goes. I had saved something
or different I thought um that if the
city engineer um determines that pave
surfacing would increase the harm to
downstream drainage.
Um one thing I would note is and is
clear in the code amendments is that the
exemptions do not apply to the federally
mandated EDA spaces. So that's why you
see at places like East Park, um you'll
see there's a concrete parking pad out
there for handicap space with unloading.
Those are what are required under the
federal rules for public publicly
accessessful facilities. That would
still be required.
And then if it blatantly doesn't fall
into the context of the area, um then
paving would be required. For example,
if we had um a church in the downtown
that wanted to um purchase a a vacant
lot um to use for overflow parking a few
times a year for certain services that
would have to fall into the development
areas of the downtown urban context. So,
this is really I'm looking at what is
the character of your neighborhood look
like. um examples I I could say where um
parking uh
would be able to remain you know gravel
and in context I can comfortably say
like the wife farms type of facility
that has that the context where gravel
would be an acceptable um parking
servicing treatment the the gravel um I
look up an area like off of Powder House
we have like the Brian church up there
near Pow outer house and story. That is
an area where it fits the context as
well. Um, another area would be there's
the um, uh, Cheyenne Hills Church
located over on on Dell Range and
Christensen. Um, that would be a
candidate where it would meet um, that
criteria as well.
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Um, Councilman Crave through you. So,
I'm looking at when I look at this um,
on page I'm sorry, these aren't
numbered, but it looks like it's uh in
proposed parking design and it's on the
fourth page
where it's primarily the entire page is
red and number four does not match what
you had on that last slide. So, is it it
it says regional storm water management
parking areas where the applicant
demonstrates to the satisfaction. This
says city engineer. That says licensed
engineer. Is it in fact the city
engineer that we want in there?
>> Okay.
>> Chair and Dr. Aldrich. Yes. I I did
clarify. I said it should say city
engineer, not license. That was a a typo
on my part.
>> And one follow-up question. I see in
here under item C where it's um there
are two areas that it's subject to the
approval by the director. And then I
also see under um 5B where um and and a
both that there are areas where the
director has um approval to approve
exceptions. Is there a reason why we
would bypass for instance the board of
adjustments who usually makes those
types of exceptions to allow the
director to do that? I'm just my concern
is that as directors come and go or as
there are changes in the office that um
we it we tend to have people who are
very concerned about consistency and
that one neighbor is held to something
different than someone else or one
business simply based on um one person
one individual's discretion
three to Dr. Aldrich. Um that's a a
great observation. Yes. Um people change
um opinions change, ways things are
interpreted change. The primary primary
reason for this was because a lot of
times um these develop during a site
plan process and administrative solution
typically is quicker and easier for
everyone to deal with. When something
has to go to the board of adjustment, it
generally has at least at minimum a
three-w weekek um headway because it has
to go through a legal ad, it has to go
through um through mail notice and such.
And then you also go to a volunteer
board which does have the
uh ability to change hands every 3 years
as new members are appointed. So really
the impetus was trying to create a path
forward that was more efficient for time
for everybody and to trying to trim the
process. Um but yes, you're correct.
There is always uncertainty with how
something something is going to be
interpreted by the director at the time
or with the board adjustment by the
board adjustment.
>> Thank you, Mr. Chair.
>> Dr. Crims.
>> Thank you. Excuse me. Thank you. Um, I
would like to reiterate what
Councilwoman Aldrich just said, um, from
the standpoint too that I think part of
the challenge that we face in many op
instances is in trying to do something
quicker, it may actually lead to more
confusion on the part of the developer
or the business people. Um, and I
encounter that in my work life all the
time that we there's a lot of fluid
fluidity that sometimes I think is
problematic. So I would um just like to
add that. But then my second question is
in regard to the gravel parking. Is it
legal to have a handicap parking space
in gravel parking? And I'm sorry I don't
know more about this, but um
do are there regulations on the size of
businesses before handicap parking
uh slots are necessary?
Chair three to Dr. Emmens. I believe I
know the answer to that, but I'm going
to have to follow up um directly. I have
to follow up on that one. That was a
little bit more complicated. Um, I do
know there I do believe that once you're
required to provide a parking place on a
site as part of a use that you have to
have an ADA space, but there are some
caveats as to what that design looks
like and when it has to be signed. Um,
so I will I'll have to follow up with
the council on that one. I want to make
sure I get the right answer out there.
>> Mr. chair. Um, I just want to make sure
that again we're not being confusing by
telling people no, you can do gravel,
but then turn around and say except for
and if there is an except for, that's
okay. I just want to make sure that
we're being clear. So, thank you for
following up.
>> Um, Jennifer, we have some a question
online.
>> Yeah. Well, uh, yes, Mr. Chairman,
through you. uh just to provide some
clarification to my colleague uh there
is and I don't know the specific number
of spaces or or what have you but I know
for a fact that according to the public
rightway access proag which is kind of
what governs those things it is not
illegal to have a disabled uh parking
spot in a gravel parking area. Now
dimensions or what have you I I I can't
speak to that. I could probably find out
from a colleague at my day job, but um
yeah, it's it is definitely allowed and
I know specific examples from around the
state.
>> Thank you, Councilman
Director
and chair, members of council. This is
probably the easiest one to understand
here and to chat about. This is an
electrical fence exemption. Right now,
the only exemption that we have for
electric fences in the city is in
conjunction with our uh goat uh grazing,
the weed management that we do, which is
very popular. Um so this would be the
addition of another subsection to
municipal code 91280.
um which basically allows for um any uh
for electric fencing to be used for the
containment or management of any
livestock. Um provided that that fencing
is not located within a public rideway,
which fencing shouldn't be in the public
rightway anyway. Um if it's um not
um like along a public trail side, um
not located within a public rideway, a
public sidewalk, trail or pedestrian
easement. Um and then that warning sites
will need to be posted at reasonable
interview intervals that don't exceed
100 feet. Um notifying folks that that
is electrified fence. Um this is a
pretty simple um amendment that would
allow for electrified fences to be
installed.
So the the final change will be um
another change to municipal code. Uh and
this is one that is in regard to keeping
a slaughtering of animals. The title is
a lot longer. Um, but right now it says
that you that it is prohibited to keep
and slaughter animals in the city of
Cheyenne unless you're in an
agricultural zone district. So, what
we've done is we've modified it um to
basically say and then this is the this
is the exemptions. This is spelled out
on the
final page of your packet.
is the exact same thing here.
So, this clarifies
um that
you can keep and slaughter animals in
the agricultural
uh agricultural residential and the
rural residential zones.
Um you can do that on sites that have an
approved conditional use or a site plan
for the use that specifically includes
livestock operations as part of that
approval. So for example, if you are in
the industrial zone district and you are
approved for a slaughter house or
confined feeding operation, then you
would be able to keep animals at that
location.
Um we have also added item number seven
um which clarifies that if an area was
subject to an agricultural use or
grazing um and it was lawful within one
year prior to an annexation or change in
zoning that it could continue continue.
So, for example, if we had areas, say in
the Swan Ranch, um the High High Plains
Business Park, those type of areas that
where grazing was occurring, that those
could continue um upon annexation. Um
that is just further clarification
um that that use could occur um because
right now it would be allowed under
state statute because it's a
non-conforming use that would be able to
continue. That's just further
clarification under the code that it
could occur. Um we all may recognize
more recently
and remember recently we had section 20
when we annexed them they had a explicit
concern regarding the the grazing um on
their land. Um this would cover a
scenario like that as well.
>> Dr. Aldridge,
>> Councilman Crave through you. Um I am
having a little bit of heartburn over
the slaughtering piece here and I'll
tell you why. When we lived at CSU in
married student housing, we had students
who were of a cultural persuasion where
goats were commonly used um for some of
their um
occasions. And there was a a common use
of sl or common practice of slaughtering
these goats in the bathtubs of student
housing. And it it caused major issues
with um sewage and drainage. Have we run
this by BOPU or had any conversation
with them? I I mean, I'm just thinking
about if we have residential areas where
we have slaughtering being done and I
know that right now people do that when
they hunt or you know that when they've
bagged an animal and then they're
slaughtering their own animal, but when
you're talking about doing it what could
be as a business, I I just think that
this opens up kind of a Pandora's box.
And I know that CSU spent thousands upon
thousands of dollars in plumbing issues
in married student housing because of
slaughtering of goats and bathtubs. And
I just think that this may be something
that Board of Public Utilities needs to
weigh in on.
>> Mr. Chair,
>> Dr. Emmens,
>> is there a need for a different
definition? I mean, there's slaughtering
and then there's butchering,
>> processing,
>> or processing. You know, I remember
having an elk hanging in my garage being
processed and now I don't know that it
was legal or not, but
long time ago. Um, but it wasn't being
slaughtered at my home. It was just
being processed at my home, which I
think is what we want, right?
>> Director and chair, members of council,
I'm I'm understanding the the
conversation here about trying to
differentiate the two and that is a note
that I can take back because we have a
couple different things here. We have
the large scale operations, which those
are very clear. Those are large
facilities that are noticeable. Um, and
then we have the processing of an
animal, which is one you bring home
after a successful weekend hunting trip
or someone in your family or friends
did. And then you have the other
portion, which is butchering of an
animal um on site, you know, which could
be your own animal. Um, we can take a
stab at trying to
poor choice of words. But we can look at
alternatives
um language on or ways to differentiate
those three to try to to slide those in
there.
And again, this this whole
this whole scenario, this whole thing
here is um just to get some feedback
from you, get some feedback from the
public um to
see if
you feel like we are moving in the right
direction with this ordinance and if
there are any changes we need to make.
And I've heard a couple of concerns from
you all so far that we will need to
address and we're going to continue to
move forward and and make those changes.
One of those being the most latter.
And I apologize if there's any confusion
with this. I'm getting over a a sickness
today. Well, like not today. Like I was
sick earlier this week. So still not
firing on all cylinders right now
unfortunately. We do have a question
online. Jennifer.
>> Uh yeah, Mr. chair through you. I just
just a comment. I just wanted to thank
you, Charles, and thank thank your
staff. Um I know that this really
is a major effort, but long overdue, uh
long needed. Um our our current um
ordinances are just so outdated. So, the
time that you and your staff took in uh
making this effort is is appreciated.
Um, you know, I think four or five of us
asked you guys to work on this and and
you've delivered. Um, I don't think uh
we're finished and I'm sure there's
going to be some amendments and some
modifications made as as the process
moves forward, but um I know it was a
heavy lift, especially considering
everything else going on in your office
and and just wanted to thank you and
your staff.
Mr.
>> Chair, Dr. Ern,
>> thank you. Um I want to echo that and
also um highlight the fact that we had
made a commitment to having an a new
classification with the urban farms and
you know I think this
honors that commitment which I really
appreciate and hope others in the
community will as well because it is
another opportunity which is what we
talked about many months ago is it's one
more opport opportunity within the city.
Um, so I'm very excited about it and the
fact that we were able to get it this
far and hopefully carry it through and
thank you so much,
>> Dr. Aldridge.
>> Uh, Chairman Crave through you. I would
echo um my colleagues that I do
appreciate the work that your team has
put in on this and I think that it
really helps to um
lay the foundation for entrepreneurial
activity in our community and to
encourage um that type of activity. Um,
will we have an opportunity as a council
to see the public's comments and to also
see whatever the
revision is prior to it coming to us as
a resolution?
>> Director
chair through Dr. Aldridge. Yes, that's
a a great question. Um, right now this
is on connect Cheyenne and it is open
for any public any member of the public
to make a comment. Um, as of this
morning when I looked at it, we had no
public comments that have been noted on
that page. Um, we will, um, inform you
all of any public comments we receive.
Um, and we will note any changes that we
make from this presentation um, to what
goes forward to you all in the future.
And just as a process note, the only
pieces that the planning commission will
be reviewing are the unified development
code related items, the ones that are um
amendments to the uh municipal code,
which is uh number three and number
four, electric fences and general
agriculture. Those are municipal
ordinances. So they will be married to
the entire package after planning
commission consideration.
>> Okay. But yes, we'll keep you notified.
>> Dr.
>> What followup? Um I was just thinking
about this, Councilman Crave, that um
this might be a a great topic um and a
great initial topic for our new social
media expert to think about putting out
on social media. um because if we
haven't gotten any comments um on this
that's concerning I think because Lord
knows we will have comments when it
comes before the council. So
>> completely agree.
>> I'm I'm sure that uh he is listening. I
see him listening and I'm sure that will
happen and further uh comments or
questions for the director Bloom. Any uh
Councilman White, Dr. Renie, any
questions?
>> None for me, sir. Thank you. Have a good
weekend.
No, Mr. President. Thank you.
>> All right. Anything else,
Jennifer? Okay.
>> With that, uh, we are adjourned. I
appreciate you all coming today. Thank
you so much.
>> I'm happy you're feeling better.
>> Yeah.
Kind of scary, isn't it? I went to the
doctor was in the hospital
and